

JASON GANNON

Technical Writing | API Design & Documentation

765.615.6332 | jason.gannon@protonmail.com | linkedin.com/in/jasonmgannon | github.com/jasongannon

Professional Summary

Versatile technical writer, API designer, and software developer with over 15 years' experience in the software industry. Expertise in user & developer documentation. Expertise in the OpenAPI Specification and REST API design. Extensive experience in fintech, including banking and payments (PCI DSS). Strong background in security, data privacy, and regulatory compliance. Enjoy collaborating with stakeholders to improve the user experience of APIs, software, and documentation.

Skills

- Technical Documentation
- API Design & Documentation
- User Experience; Developer Experience
- Fintech: Banking, Payments (PCI DSS)
- Security; Data Privacy; Regulatory Compliance
- Technical Writing & Editing
- Markdown, HTML, CSS, JavaScript
- Information Architecture; Content Modeling
- Change Management & Version Control
- SDLC; Agile Methodologies

Professional Experience

Qualtrics

Senior Technical Analyst (Technical Writing)

Mar 2022-Sep 2024

Led API design, documentation, and governance programs to improve the quality of public APIs.

- Developed and managed an API design guide and API rulesets to improve site consistency.
- Integrated Spectral API linter from Stoplight into our CI/CD pipeline (GitLab/Jenkins.
- Improved accuracy and concision of API documentation—40% reduction in support tickets.
- · Created public API Collections on Postman API, which won Postman's award for Best New API for 2024.

United Parcel Service (UPS)

Senior Technical Analyst (Technical Writing)

Sep 2023-Feb 2024

Led API design, documentation, and governance programs to improve the quality of public APIs.

- Implemented custom Spectral linter for API validation to make sure OASs were correct and consistent.
- Refactored public OAS documentation to improve validation rates with the OpenAPI 3.x standard.
- Developed a web app prototype for a new developer portal, increasing product teams' satisfaction.

Pace Software

Senior Technical Writer

Sep 2021-Jul 2023

API design and documentation. Led development of developer portal for fintech startup (mobile payments).

- Designed and documented public APIs to speed up integration with payment processors.
- Developed a JSON-based rules engine for logic processing, which reduced system.
- · Handled all compliance documentation for PCI DSS audits and certifications.

Conduent

Senior Technical Analyst (Technical Writing)

Sep 2017-Sep 2021

Developed content models, documentation, and learning plans for enterprise web applications.

- Developed content models, document models, and a task roadmap that sped up employee onboarding.
- Ensured software and documentation updates were in 100% compliance with industry regulations.

Self-Employed

Technical Writer; Web Developer

Oct 2010-Present

Technical documentation and web development services for web and mobile applications (banking).

- Developed responsive web applications during early days of mobile banking applications.
- Created RESTful web services for financial applications to improve customer experience.

The Korte Company

Preconstruction Manager

Sep 2004-Sep 2010

Construction manager for commercial construction industry. Estimation, scheduling, project management.

Education

Purdue University, West Lafayette, Indiana Bachelor of Arts—English Literature

May 2004

Tools

- Documentation: Markdown, LaTex, AsciiDoc, reStructuredText
- API Tools: Swagger, Postman, Stoplight, Redoc, Spectral linter
- Languages: C, Go, SQL, Rust, JavaScript, HTML & CSS
- Frameworks: React, Next.js, Astro, Svelte, Node.js, Express.js, .NET
- Diagramming: Visio, Lucidchart, draw.io, PlantUML, Mermaid JS
- Version Control: Git, GitHub, GitLab

Certifications

- · OpenAPI Initiative (OAI) Certified OpenAPI Specialist
- · API Documentation Certification
- Postman API Certification
- PCI DSS Compliance Fundamentals

Sample Projects

- Pace Software Developer Portal & API Reference
- Integrating with RuleEngine
- Spectral API Linter Web Application
- Linking to Your Postman API Collection

For sample projects, please visit: github.com/jasongannon/work-samples